A Finding Aid to the Louis Pomerantz Papers, 1937-1988, bulk 1950s-1988, in the Archives of American Art aaa.pomeloui
Archives of American Art
Louis Pomerantz papers
bulk 1950-1988
1937-1988
aaa.pomeloui
Archives of American Art
34.1 Linear feet
The papers of Chicago art conservator, Louis Pomerantz, measure 34.1 linear feet and date from 1937 to 1988, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1950s-1980s. The papers document two principal aspects of Pomerantz's professional life: his conservation work for institutions and individuals, and the development of his professional expertise as documented through his writings and teachings, his continued conservation training, and his involvement in professional organizations. Files include scattered biographical material, professional correspondence, interviews, writings, project and client files, teaching and reference files, printed material, and photographic material primarily documenting conservation treatments and techniques.
Pomerantz, Louis
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington D.C. research center. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers. Use of audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical/Historical note
Chicago art conservator Louis Pomerantz (1919-1988), established and operated the conservation lab at the Art Institute of Chicago and then maintained a private practice conducting conservation work for individual collectors and various museums and art institutions in the midwest.
Pomerantz had originally intended to be an artist and enrolled at the Art Students League. After serving in World War II, he returned to Europe to study conservation as an apprentice to a private restorer in Paris, followed by a year spent working under the chief restorer at the Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam, and study at the Courtauld Institute and the National Gallery in London. As head of the Art Institute of Chicago's first conservation lab from 1956-1961, Pomerantz employed new and emerging techniques such as powerful binocular microscopes, ultra-violet, infra-red and X-ray machines to study paintings, and a hot table to bond new canvasses to support old ones. Following his resignation from the Art Institute of Chicago to pursue his private practice, Pomerantz organized conservation training programs, and wrote widely on conservation. He served on the American Institute for Conservation of Historic and Artistic Works (AIC) and was a member of the committee which adopted the AIC's first code of ethics for art conservators in May 1967. He became consultant to various art and natural history museums including the Field Museum of Natural History in Chicago, where he formed part of the conservation team that completed an extensive renovation of the museum's Javanese gamelan ensemble composed of 23 brass and wood musical instruments.The gamelan was presented and played for the first time since 1893 in 1978, following the restoration.
Pomerantz also organized several museum exhibitions on conservation, including Know What You See, which was shown at more than 100 museums around the United States, Canada and Mexico, as part of the Smithsonian Institution Traveling Exhibition Service (SITES).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Louis Pomerantz papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Else Pomerantz in 1988.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Chicago art conservator, Louis Pomerantz, measure 34.1 linear feet and date from 1937 to 1988, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1950s-1980s. The papers document two principal aspects of Pomerantz's professional life: his conservation work for institutions and individuals, and the development of his professional expertise as documented through his writings and teachings, his continued conservation training, and his involvement in professional organizations. Files include scattered biographical material, professional correspondence, interviews, writings, project and client files, teaching and reference files, printed material, and photographic material primarily documenting conservation treatments and techniques.
Biographical material includes military and educational records, as well as resumés and references from various art institutions and individuals.
Pomerantz's professional correspondence is with other conservators including Anton J. Konrad, Nathan Stolow, and Jean Volkmer, conservation scientists such as Robert L. Feller, and people who assisted Pomerantz early in his career such as George Stout. Also documented is Pomerantz's relationship with the Smithsonian Institution Traveling Exhibition Service (SITES) which undertook his traveling Know What You See exhibition, his involvement with museums and other art institutions, and companies who developed and manufactured conservation equipment such as Eastman Kodak.
Interviews include circa 9 radio station interviews on sound tape reels and sound cassettes of Pomerantz individually or with others, including a recording of a conversation regarding the Florence flood.
Writings and notes are by Pomerantz and include typescripts, notes and background material for lectures and papers delivered from the 1950s-1980s. Also found is a portfolio of his writings from 1962-1978, and a notebook Pomerantz compiled while working at the Rijksmuseum which includes notes, hand-drawn colored illustrations and photographs of conservation techniques.
Project/client files form the largest series and document Pomerantz's work, both in private practice and as conservator at the Art Institute of Chicago, through conditions reports, recommendations for and records of treatment, related correspondence, financial documentation, and photographic material.
Teaching and reference files comprise material gathered by Pomerantz during participation in professional organizations and events, such as the American Institute for Conservation of Historic and Artistic Works, and the International Institute for Conservation of Historic and Artistic Works. Also found are subject files, consisting of reference material and correspondence, on a wide range of conservation-related subjects.
Personal business records from the 1950s consist of receipts for conservation-related supplies and one folder of business tax records.
Printed material primarily includes news clippings documenting Pomerantz's career up to and including the 1970s, clippings on conservation-related news, blank postcards of artwork, and two exhibition catalogs.
Photographic material includes images demonstrating a wide variety of conservation techniques, including sets of slides used for lectures and presentations, and images of Pomerantz at work. Also found are photos of artists including Ulfert Wilke. Photographic media include black and white and color photos, slides, glass slides, X-rays and corresponding prints, negatives and 5 glass plate negatives.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 9 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1940s-1980s (12 folders; Boxes 1, 33)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1940s-1988 (3.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-4)
Series 3: Interviews, 1961-circa 1970s (8 folders; Box 4)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1950s-1980s (2.8 linear feet; Box 7)
Series 5: Project/Client Files, 1950s-1987 (13.8 linear feet; Boxes 7-20)
Series 6: Teaching and Reference Files, 1940s-1980s (3.9 linear feet; Boxes 20-24)
Series 7: Personal Business Records, 1950s (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 24-25)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1937-1970s (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 25, 33)
Series 9: Photographic Material, 1940s-1980s (8.4 linear feet; Boxes 25-36, OV 37, MGP 1)
American Institute for Conservation of Historic and Artistic Works.; Art Institute of Chicago.; Eastman Kodak Company.; Feller, Robert L.; International Institute for Conservation of Historic and Artistic Works.; Konrad, Anton; Rijksmuseum (Netherlands); Smithsonian Institution. Traveling Exhibition Service.; Stolow, Nathan; Stout, George L. (George Leslie); Wilke, Ulfert, 1907-1987; Art--Conservation and restoration--Study and teaching; Art--Conservation and restoration--Technique; Conservators--Illinois--Chicago; Flood damage--Italy--Florence; Illustrations; Interviews; Museum conservation methods--Study and teaching; Museum conservation methods--Technique; Photographs; Sound recordings
- Biographical Material, 1940s-1980s; Series 1; 12 Folders Boxes 1, 33
  Scope and Contents note
  Education records document Pomerantz's studies at the Art Students League, the Brooklyn Museum, and Clark University, and his work in Paris under conservator Tito G. Satinover.
  Grants and scholarships include a 1951 application for a Fulbright scholarship. Letters of recommendation include letters sent to various educational institutions requesting educational opportunities for Pomerantz from H. Ruhemann of the Courtauld Institute of Art, in addition to references from others including Edith Halpert of Downtown Gallery, Augustus Peck of the Brooklyn Museum, and Dr. A. van Schendel of the Rijksmuseum.
  Also found are military records including Pomerantz's honorable discharge, resumés from the 1950s, and miscellaneous items such as photocopies of 12 caricatures ink sketches by Pomerantz, a recording of Ruth Howard reading poetry, 5 unidentified sound recordings on 1 sound cassette and 4 tape reels, and an unidentified watercolor.
  - Caricatures by Pomerantz (Photocopies), circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Education Records, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Grants and Scholarships, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters of Recommendation, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Military Records, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Poetry Reading by Ruth Howard, 1974; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Resume Information, 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified Sound Recordings, circa 1960s; 4 sound tape reels; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Unidentified Watercolor housed in Box 33, Folder 1, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oversized Unidentified Watercolor from Box 1, Folder 11 (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1940s-1988; Series 2; 3.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-4
  Primarily professional in nature, Pomerantz's correspondence is with friends and colleagues, museums and other art and educational institutions, and companies and corporations involved in the development of conservation tools and equipment.
  Three folders of early career correspondence, primarily from the 1950s when Pomerantz was studying on the GI Bill, document Pomerantz's applications for jobs, apprenticeships, and work/study positions. They include correspondence with George Stout of the Worcester Art Museum, and Veterans Administration records.
  The series includes six folders of correspondence with influential conservation scientist, Robert L. Feller, regarding technical issues and picture varnishes; seven folders of correspondence with forensic document examiner Linton Godown; three folders of correspondence with microscopy expert Walter C. McCrone; and correspondence with other art conservators including Anton J. Konrad, Russell J. Quandt, Bernard Rabin, Suzanne Sack, Nathan Stolow, Jean Volkmer, and Phoebe Dent Weil.
  Also found is correspondence with companies including Eastman Kodak regarding radiography techniques; museums and other art institutions including the National Gallery of Canada, Philadelphia Museum of Art, Rijksmuseum, and Rosary College Graduate School of Fine Arts which operated a conservation program in Florence, Italy; and scattered correspondence with artists such as Janice Lefton de Luigi. Correspondence with the Smithsonian's SITES and participating institutions documents the 1980s Know What You See touring exhibition.
  Correspondence relating to Pomerantz's work for the Art Institute of Chicago can be found in Series 5: Project/Client Files.
  The series contains 2 sound recordings of television broadcasts on 2 sound cassettes.
  Arrangement note
  Records are arranged alphabetically by folder title, primarily by name but occasionally by subject such as "Early Career Correspondence." 5 folders of unsorted correspondence from the 1970s can be found filed under "U."
  - Adelberg, Peter, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Allentown Art Museum, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Asian Conservation Laboratory, Inc., 1960s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bakelite Company, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Balboa Art Conservation Center, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Barker, Elvera, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Battoli, Lucy, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Beckman, Tom, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Belgian American Educational Foundation, Inc., 1960s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Belgian Consulate General, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Board of Jewish Education, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Boissonnas, Alain C. (Fine Arts Conservation Lab), 1950s-1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bridgeman, Charles F. (Eastman Kodak Company), 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - British National Committee of the International Council of Museums, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Causa, Raffaello, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chicago Section American Chemical Society, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chicago Tribune, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Christopher & Tooker, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cincinnati Art Museum, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Courtauld Institute of Art, 1956, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Crawford, Charles, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Denglas, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dougherty, Ruth, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - E. Leitz, Inc., 1950s (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Early Career Correspondence, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 37-39)
  - Eastman Kodak Company, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Ednalite Optical Co., Inc., 1960s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Evanston Art Center, 1966-1976 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Feller, Robert L., 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 43-48)
  - Fernandez, Orlando Seitas, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Fieux Restoration Laboratory (Robert E. Fieux), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    includes original print by Robert E. Fieux
  - Fishburne, S. Julian, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Fisher, Margaret and Thomas, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Fogg Art Museum, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Forest Products Laboratory, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Georges de La Tour Controversy, 1980s; Includes 2 sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Georges de La Tour Controversy, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Gettens, Rutherford J., 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Giminez Carrazana, Manuel, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Godown, Linton, 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 6-12)
  - Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hahn Bros. Fireproof Warehouses, Inc., 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Harry Weese and Associates, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Hodgkinson, Ian, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Hulmer, Eric, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hurtig, Martyn, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Huth, Hans, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hyde Park-Kenwood Community Conference, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - I. R. Viewer (FJW Industries), 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Illinois Arts Council, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Institut Royal d Patimoine Artistique, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Institute of International Education, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - International Institute for the Conservation of Museum Objects, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Iowa Arts Council, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (Guldbeck, Per E.), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Joslyn Art Museum, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Kaye, Saul, 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Keisch, Bernard, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Kennedy, Ellen Dickson, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Kennedy, Ralph, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Klindt, Steven L., 1970s (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Konrad, Anton J., 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
  - Korany, Edward O., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Krisel, Harold and Rose, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Laboratoire Central Des Musees de Belgique, 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Lawrence University, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Lefton de Luigi, Janice, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
    Includes original artwork by Lefton
  - Lennon, Timothy,Transfer Technique, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Levine, Jack, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Levinson, Rustin, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Louvre Museum, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Martyl (Mrs. Alexander Langsdorf, Jr.), 1960s (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - McCrone, Walter C. (McCrone Associates), 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 47-49)
  - McNabb, Allan, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Mellon Institute (Rob Feller, Gregory Nelson), 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Mensh, H. L., 1960s (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Mertens, Har, 1966-1981 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Midwest Regional Conservation Guild, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Milwaukee Public Museum, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Minewski, Alex, 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Misbach, Elizabeth, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mitka, Wieslaw and Isabelle, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Miyoko, Ito, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Moorehead State University, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Nathans, Jerome, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - National Gallery, London, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Gallery of Art, 1957-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Gallery of Canada, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - National Park Service Murals Bid, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New Art Examiner, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - North County Museum of Arts, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Northern Illinois Human Services Corporation, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Olin, Charles, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Olin, Jacqueline, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Orraca, Jose, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Packard, Anthony, 1960s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Packard, Elisabeth C. G., 1950s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Parker, Stearns & Company, Inc., 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Perkins, Ed (Butler Institute of American Art), 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Perot, Paul N., 1980s (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Pollack, Herbert, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Politicians and Public Officials, Letters to, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Polk Community College, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Pollack, Herbert, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Postcards, 1940s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Primitive Art Society, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Professional Picture Framers Association, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Quandt, Russell J. and Eleanor, 1905s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - R. M. Stephens & Co., Inc., 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - R. R. Bowker Company, Fine Arts Market Place, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Rabin, Bernard, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Rabin, Bernard, Reports of Treatment, 1960s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Rajer, Anton William, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Ralph Mayer Center for Artists' Techniques, 1960s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Rijksmuseum, 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Robertson, Clements L. and James Roth, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Rosary College Graduate School of Fine Arts, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
  - Rujemann, Helmut, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Sack, Suzanne P., 1950s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Saint Mary's College, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Sandberg W. (Stedelijk Museum), 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Savestone Corporation (Stone Preservative), 1970s (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Schenck, Mary, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Schnorr, Emil G., 1984 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Schwartzbaum, Paul M., 1970s (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Sears, Roebuck & Co., 1970s (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Sebara, Donald K., 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Siegel, Theodor, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Smith, Richard D., 1987 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Smithsonian Institution Conservation Analytical Laboratory, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Smithsonian Institution Traveling Exhibition Service (SITES), 1980s (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Society of American Archivists, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - South Carolina Museum Commission, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Southside Historic Preservation Fund, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Stewart, Norman, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Stolow, Nathan, 1950s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 60-62)
  - Stoner, Joyce Hill (American Institute for Conservation), 1970s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Strilky, Rick, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Tahk, Christopher, 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Tam, Reuben (about Tam), 1980s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tarrant, Alice and Irving, 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tate Gallery, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Time (Robert Hughes), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Tribolet, Harold W., 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - University of Delaware, Ralph Mayer Center, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Unsorted Correspondence, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 11-15)
  - van Schendel, Arthur (Rijksmuseum), 1950s (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Volkmer, Jean (Museum of Modern Art), 1950s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Vunjak, Michel, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Walter R. Ratai, Inc., 1983 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Washington University, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Watherston, Margaret, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Weidner, Marilyn Kemp, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Weil, Phoebe Dent, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Who's Who In America, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - William Rainey Harper College, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Wolf, Sara J., 1980s (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Interviews, 1961-circa 1970s; Series 3; 8 Folders Box 4
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
  Series consists of sound recordings of interviews with Pomerantz alone, or featuring Pomerantz, including 4 interviews with Bob Elson of Radio WCFL conducted between 1960 and 1962, with a signed photo of Elson, and circa 5 additional radio station interviews, including a "conversation with Saul Kaye, Harold Tribolet, Paul Banks, Lou Pomerantz" regarding the Florence flood.
  Recordings are on 9 sound tape reels and 2 sound cassettes.
  - Canadian Broadcasting Company, 1961; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "Interview with Lonnie by Dad 4/24/72", 1972; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Problem of Fungicides in Florence Flood, 1967; 2 sound tape reels (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Radio Station KCCM, circa 1970s; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Radio Station WAAF Chicago, circa 1960; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Radio Station WCFL, Pump Room Program with Bob Elson, 1960-1962; 4 sound tape reels (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
  - Radio Station WTMJ Milwaukee, 1963; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Writings and Notes, 1950s-1980s; Series 4; 2.8 Linear feet Box 7
  This series documents Pomerantz's contributions to the field of art conservation through papers and presentations he gave at educational institutions, professional conferences, and seminars. Found are typescripts for lectures and presentations, course material, outlines, notes, related material, and sound recordings.
  Lectures and papers listed alphabetically by title are all by Pomerantz. Several folders relate to diffrerent iterations of a lecture that ultimately resulted in the exhibition Know What You See circulated by SITES, including draft manuscripts and notes for "Learning to See," "Truth in Seeing" and "Know What You See."